Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls, 1700-1900: Finding Aid C0744.04
Manuscripts Division
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 37, 1870-1930; 37; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven and untutored hand (5mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  3 bands of 3 squares each, the top and bottom with alternate checkerboard and transverse cross designs, the middle band with a face in the center square, (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  3 human figures. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Gäbre'él (f.)
  - Prayer for Confounding Demons (Mäshäberomu [sic] Lä'aganent), Devils and Barya, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos for the Protection of Suckling Infants and Mothers Whose Children Do Not Survive. Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Phanuel, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 38, 1830-1870; 38; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a dense but reasonable hand (4mm), slightly rubbed and faded in parts. 5 talismanic drawings and 2 decorative bands. (Box 1)
  Cross in hand cross form with two smaller crosses either side. (In ink with some red color, now faded.)
  Derivative of the eight-pointed star design, here reduced to a central face surrounded by decorated squares with lobed extensions above and below, set between bands of squares with faces and transverse cross motifs. (In ink with some red color, now faded.)
  Grid of 12 squares alternately containing lobed transverse crosses with eye-motifs and faces. (In ink with red and yellow color, now faded.)
  3 rows of 3 squares each containing a face. (In ink with red and yellow color, now faded.)
  Grid of 9 squares with a face in the center square and 'sun faces' in the four corner squares, the others with striated infill. (In ink with red and yellow color, now faded.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Gäbrä Egzi'abehér ? (m.), has been replaced by others, one of which may be read as Wäldä Maryam (m.)
  - Prayer for the Undoing of Spells (Fethatä Seray) and against Spirits That Cause Various Ailments, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Satan, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Stopping of Spells "By Craft or by Women (Legwemomu Läserayä Ed Wä'anest), That Neither Muslim, Christian Nor Jew Be Hidden." Prayer against Colic, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 39, 1770-1799; 39; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together (the bottom piece is now attached by a pair of threads only.) 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven hand (3-5mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red, yellow and blue-grey color, now much faded.)
  Derivative of the eight-pointed star design (?), or possibly a cherub: a central face with 4 wings each ending in a bird's or serpent's head, and a human figure above and below (the latter inverted). (In ink with faded red, yellow and blue-grey color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with faded red, yellow, grey-brown and blue wash color.)
  Another eight-pointed star design. (In ink with faded red, yellow, grey-brown and blue wash color.) Beneath is a single line of text continuing from the last line above the drawing, 'for nothing is impossible for God.'
  Owner: Newayä Maryam (m.)
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya, Mäqqañña and Serayäñña, Incorporating the Text Known as the Net of Solomon or the Secret Names of Solomon (Asmatä Sälomon), late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayers for Undoing Spells, late 18th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 40, dates not examined; 40; 1 box 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (3-4mm). 4 talismanic drawings plus 2 talismanic figures inserted in the text. 1760 x 110mm (Box 1)
  Contains in continuo: Prayer for undoing spells; various prayers against the evil eye, including those of "black and red people, Jews, pagans, Moslems, and Christians ... priests and deacons"; various prayers against foul légéwon, as well as barya.
  Grid of 9 squares with faces in 5, forming a cruciform pattern and wings (?) in the remaining 4. (In ink with red and possibly yellow color, now faded.)
  Derivative of the eight-pointed star design with a central face and circles and crescents (?) in the four corners. (In ink with red and yellow color, now faded.)
  Human figure with raised arms and two seraphim either side. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Rough grid design within a frame of crosses and brackets. (In ink with red color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name has been replaced by that of Wälättä Sellasé (f.)
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 41, 1800-1899; 41; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top of the scroll has been cut or torn off. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a small and reasonable hand (2-3mm), framed within a linear border which shows traces of yellow color. 1 rough drawing; the original drawing at the top has been removed. (Box 1)
  Rough sketch of a cross, a spear, the sun (?) and nails or points (?), perhaps a highly stylized rendition of the Crucifixion. (In ink with red-brown color.)
  Owner: Täklä Sellasé (m.)
  - The Text Known as the Lefafä S'edq or Bandlet of Righteousness, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer of the Road to Heaven (S'älotä Mängädä Sämay), 19th century; 1 item
    Includes the sermon of Elijah.
  - Prayer of the Road to Heaven, 19th century; 1 item
  - A Further Prayer of the Road to Heaven, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 42, 1770-1799; 42; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top of the scroll has been badly damaged by rodents, as have some of the edges. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a clear hand (4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  [fragmentary] Grid with central face. (In ink with red, blue and yellow color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red, blue and yellow color.)
  Derivative of the eight-pointed star design (?), or possibly a cherub: a central face with 4 wings each ending in a bird's or serpent's head, and a human figure above and below (the latter inverted). Beside the upper figure is the name Gäbray Egzi', and by the lower figure is written emmété 'madam'. This drawing is almost identical to no. 2 scroll 39. (In ink with red, blue and yellow color.)
  Rough drawing of a figure with two smaller winged figures either side.
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Buda and Demons, late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Buda and Barya, late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Buda, late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Blacksmiths, late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for "Drowning" Barya and against the Evil Eye of Barya and Buda, late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Terror or Fear of Falling Into Deep Water, late 18th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 43, 1800-1899; 43; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable and compact hand (3mm). 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  A seraph. (in red and black ink, now soiled and faded.)
  Lozenge within a square decorated with lobed figures and protective eye-motifs. (In red and black ink.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face and eye-motifs at the ends of each arm. (In red and black ink.)
  Owner: to the original owner's name, Amätä Mika'él (f.), has been later added that of Wälättä Kidan (f.)
  - Prayer of Susenyos; Legend of Susenyos; Prayers against Hemorrhage Incorporating the Story of the Woman With an Issue of Blood, 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo. Untitled. The story of the woman is purportedly drawn from the Gospels of Matthew, Mark and Luke.
  - Prayer against Miscarriage, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 44, 1770-1830; 44; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (4-5mm), framed within a linear border with traces of yellow wash. 4 well executed talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Large grid of 9 squares with a central face and eye-motifs in the 4 corner squares, the remaining squares with transverse cross designs; the whole set between two checkerboard bands. (In ink with black, red, pale yellow and olive green color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword and 2 seraphim; the whole set between bands decorated with highly stylized face motifs. (In ink with black, red, pale yellow and pale green color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face and eye-motifs at the ends of each arm. (In ink with black, red, pale yellow and pale green color.)
  World serpent ("ourobouros") design of two serpents in a circle each biting the other's tail, framed within a square decorated above and below with a chevron pattern. (In ink with black, red, pale yellow and pale green color.)
  A fish (In ink and without color.)
  Owner: As'ädä Maryam (f.), occasionally with her father's name added, Haylä Maryam.
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Evil Spirits, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
    Untitled. Comprises mostly magic or secret names (asmat).
  - Prayer against Buda, Barya and Légéwon, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Shotälay and Shotälayt, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Nädära "Which Is the Sickness of the Evil Eye of Evil Demons", circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Blacksmiths, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism and (Chest) Pain, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Plague (Or typhoid: Féra) and Fever, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 45, 1870-1899; 45; incomplete]Single piece of parchment, forming the bottom part of a scroll, the rest now missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (in purple ink) in a mediocre hand (3mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 1 talismanic drawing. (Box 2)
  Drawing: Hand cross. (In ink with yellow color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Rämha Sellasé (?) has been replaced by that of Wälättä Rufa'él (f.)
  - End of a Prayer against Buda. Series of 3 Prayers against Terror Caused by Demons (Dengas'é Aganent), late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons "Which Alexander (Esender [sic]) the King Spoke on Friday Before Gog and Magog", late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Blacksmiths, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against (Chest) Pain, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 46, 1850-1899; 46; incomplete]Single piece of parchment forming the top portion of a scroll, the rest now missing. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics in an untidy and spidery hand (), framed between a linear border with traces of yellow color and separated by a central margin with chevron designs in red, blue and yellow. 2 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red, yellow, black and blue color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name has been erased and replaced with that of Wälättä Ananya (f.)
  - Prayer for the Drowning of Demons, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and "All Evil Spirits", Incorporating the Text Known as the Net of Solomon, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 47, 1850-1899; 47; incomplete]Single piece of parchment, forming the top portion of a scroll, the rest now missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a large and somewhat unsophisticated hand (5mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 1 talismanic drawing. (Box 2)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with yellow color.)
  A band of decoration at the bottom probably formed part of a drawing on the now missing second portion of the scroll.
  - Account Drawn from the Gospel of Matthew of the Woman Whose Daughter Was Seized by a Demon, Followed by an Invocation for Salvation from "The Terror of the Devil", circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against "The Bonds of the Face of Death", circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Terror, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 48, late 18th century; 48; 1 box 2 pieces of parchment sewn together; the bottom piece shows repairs to a natural hole before writing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an angular and compact hand (3-4mm), framed within a linear border. 1 talismanic drawing. 1120 x 110mm (Box 2)
  Contains the text Known as the Temhertä Hebu'at or Doctrina Arcanorum.
  Drawing: Grid of 9 squares with a central face, and alternating transverse cruciform motifs and pairs of squares with circles at the center. (In ink with yellow color.)
  Owner: the original owner was Segutä Sellasé (f.), but a second name, Wälättä Abbiyä Egzi' (f.), has been added later.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 49, circa 1870-1930; 49; 1 box A single piece of parchment. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 2 talismanic drawings. Preserved within a leather cylinder pouch (1 piece) and attached by a leather thong to the pouch containing scroll 50. 660 x 55mm (Box 2)
  Contains in continuo: prayer for the binding of demons, devils, zar, tegrida and buda ... "A Prayer Which Alexander the King Spoke Before Gog and Magog"; prayer against rheumatism, colic, typhoid, fever and other ailments.
  Guardian angel with a drawn sword (only the scabbard is visible). (In ink with yellow, blue and pale red color.)
  Hand cross. (In ink with yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Maryam (f.)
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 50, 1800-1899; 50; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an angular and untidy hand (5mm), framed within a wide linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. Preserved within a leather cylinder pouch (2 pieces) attached by a leather thong to the pouch containing scroll 49. (Box 2)
  2 guardian angels with drawn swords separated by a central margin. (In ink with yellow and pale red wash.
  2 further guardian angels with drawn swords separated by a central margin. (In ink with yellow and pale red wash.
  2 further guardian angels with drawn swords separated by a central margin. Beneath them are 11 squares containing stylized faces. (In ink with yellow and pale red wash.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Esétä Selläsé (f.), has been lightly erased and replaced with that of Wälättä Egzi' (f.)
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya and Légéwon, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Shotälay, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 51, 1800-1899; 51; 3 pieces of coarse parchment sewn together. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics in an untidy hand (3-5mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow and separated by a central margin with a chevron design in red and yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Eight-pointed star design in grid format. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Derivative of the eight –pointed star design: the central face and topmost and bottommost arm are reduced to a single ellipse, whilst the four corner arms appear as curved extensions and the remaining two arms appear as small chevrons; the whole is surrounded by concentric circles. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  A more conventional eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Wäldä Mika'él (m.), has been overwritten by that of Wälättä Haymanot (f.) or Wälättä Giyorgis (f.)
  - The Text Known as the Net of Solomon, or Secret Names of Solomon (Here Asmat Zälomon [sic]) "For Catching Demons as in a Fishing Net"; Prayers against Däsk, Barya, Gudalé, Blacksmiths, as Well as Ailments Such as Headache, Colic, Rheumatism, etc, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayers for Undoing Spells (Mäftehé Seray), 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Buda, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Personal Aggrandizement (?); Prayer For Undoing Charms, 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo. Title not fully legible due to overwriting of later owner's name.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 52, 1830-1870; 52; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven and sloping hand (3-5mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  5 vertical bands of triangles alternately colored black (or yellow) or infilled with zigzag lines.
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with yellow and russet color.)
  Guardian angel (without a sword.) (In ink with yellow and russet color.)
  Grid of 12 squares with two faces, one inverse, in the centre and variously spiral or transverse cross designs in the others. (In ink with yellow, black and russet color .) The word "Trinity" is written in the top, center square.
  Owner: the original owners' names, Wäldä Rufa'él (m.) and Wälättä Rufa'él (f.), the latter of which seems to occur only once, have been erased and replaced with that of Haylä Sellasé (m.)
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, Incorporating the Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon and for the Binding of Demons [of] the Tempest (Aganent Awlo), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Diseases of the Liver or Stomach, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against (Chest) Pain. Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Jesus' Side Pierced by the Spear of Longinus, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Contains the beginning of the Gospel of John.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 53, 1800-1899; 53; incomplete ?]2 pieces of parchment sewn together; the bottom of the scroll appears to be missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a mediocre hand (4mm). 3 talismanic drawings. Preserved in a red leather cylinder pouch (kid skin ?) colored bright red. (Box 2)
  Regal figure with two attendants (King Solomon ?). (In ink with red and yellow color, now faded.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red and yellow color, now faded.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red and yellow color, now faded.)
  Owner: Wälättä Mädhen (f.)
  - Prayer [Against Demons] Using the Secret Names (Asmat) of the Trinity, 19th century; 1 item
    The text continues with secret names given to Solomon to entrap demons "like fish in a net," and extends to various spirits and ailments. Sälam (hymn of salutation) to Phanuel.
  - Prayer against Colic, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer Invoking "The Light of the Godhead [and] the Rampart of the Cross" (Mäbräqä Mäläkotu Bähas'urä Mäsqälu) for Protection from Demons, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 54, 1800-1850; 54; 2 pieces of thin parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a widely spaced medium hand (4-5mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 2 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Pair of lozenges with cruciform design infill, one above the other and set against a ground of dots. (In red and black ink, with slight yellow wash.)
  Cruciform with apexed arms. (In ink with red and yellow color.) At the top of the figure is what looks like a brief text in Arabic.
  Above the whole is a grid of 49 squares each containing a letter (or two letters in one instance.)
  Owner: the name of the original owner has been erased and replaced with that of Wälättä Sellasé (f.)
  - The Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - The Prayer of Hannah, the Mother of Samuel the Prophet, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 55, 1800-1899; 55; A single piece of parchment. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (in reddish brown ink) in an angular and uneven hand (4-5mm),framed within a linear border (drawn in red ink). 1 talismanic drawing and 1 decorative band. Preserved within a leather cylindrical pouch (only one half now remaining.) (Box 2)
  Drawing: Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with reddish brown color.)
  At the bottom; decorative band of chevrons, transverse crosses and zigzag lines. (In black and reddish brown ink.)
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, Demons and Devils, the Evil Eye of Zar and Qurañña, Werzelya and All Evil Spirits, 19th century; 1 item
  - A Prayer for Children and Infants, 19th century; 1 item
  - A Prayer against the Evil Eye of "Red and Black [People]", 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 56, 1830-1870; 56; Two pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (now faded) in a mediocre hand (), framed within a linear border colored yellow (now faded.) 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  A central figure supported by 2 smaller figures with 2 inverted winged (?) faces above (seraphim ?) (In ink with some red color, now faded.
  Derivative of the eight-pointed star design with a central face; the whole is reduced to a cruciform with pointed arms from which spring four further curved lines outlined with a series of dots. (In ink with red and yellow wash.
  Hand cross design enclosed within a loosely rectangular frame outlined with a series of dots. (In ink with some yellow color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name has been erased and replaced with that of Gäbrä Heywät (m.)
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons "Spoken by Alexander the King Before Gog and Magog"; Prayer against (Chest) Pain, Rheumatism, Colic, Demons, Barya, Légéwon and Other Malevolent Forces; Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Phanuel; Prayers against Sorcerers and Mäqqäñña [sic], mid 19th century; 1 item
  - A Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - A Prayer against Colic, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - A Prayer against Stomach Pain, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sorcerers and Mäqqäñña, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 57, 1800-1899; 57; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (3-4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. Compare scroll no. 111, which appears to have been drawn by the same artist. (Box 2)
  Large figure (215mm) of a guardian angel with a drawn sword. (In ink with red, blue and yellow wash.)
  Another large figure (220mm) of a guardian angel with a drawn sword. (In ink with red, blue and yellow wash.)
  A pair of angelic figures standing either side of a double hand cross. (In ink with red, blue and yellow wash.)
  Owner: Gäbrä Giyorgis (m.)
  - Prayer for the Drowning of Demons and Devils, Barya and Légéwon, ... etc, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons and Devils, Zar and Tegrida ... "Spoken by Alexander the King Before Gog and Magog", 19th century; 1 item
  - A Series of Prayers for the Undoing of Spells Classified According to Regional Origin, and Occupation, 19th century; 1 item
  - A Further Prayer for the Undoing of Spells, Classified According to the Implements Used, 19th century; 1 item